<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="activechecks" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="active_checks" />Active Checks</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>&name-icinga; is capable of monitoring hosts and services in two ways: actively and passively. Passive checks are
  described <link linkend="passivechecks">elsewhere</link>, so we'll focus on active checks here. Active checks are the most
  common method for monitoring hosts and services. The main features of actives checks as as follows:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Active checks are initiated by the &name-icinga; process</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Active checks are run on a regularly scheduled basis</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/activechecks.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject></para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">How Are Active Checks Performed?</emphasis></para>

  <para>Active checks are initiated by the check logic in the &name-icinga; daemon. When &name-icinga; needs to check the status
  of a host or service it will execute a plugin and pass it information about what needs to be checked. The plugin will then check
  the operational state of the host or service and report the results back to the &name-icinga; daemon. &name-icinga; will process
  the results of the host or service check and take appropriate action as necessary (e.g. send notifications, run event handlers,
  etc).</para>

  <para>More information on how plugins work can be found <link linkend="plugins">here</link>.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">When Are Active Checks Executed?</emphasis></para>

  <para>Active check are executed:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>At regular intervals, as defined by the <emphasis>check_interval</emphasis> and <emphasis>retry_interval</emphasis>
      options in your host and service definitions</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>On-demand as needed</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Regularly scheduled checks occur at intervals equaling either the <emphasis>check_interval</emphasis> or the
  <emphasis>retry_interval</emphasis> in your host or service definitions, depending on what <link linkend="statetypes">type of
  state</link> the host or service is in. If a host or service is in a HARD state, it will be actively checked at intervals equal
  to the <emphasis>check_interval</emphasis> option. If it is in a SOFT state, it will be checked at intervals equal to the
  <emphasis>retry_interval</emphasis> option.</para>

  <para>On-demand checks are performed whenever &name-icinga; sees a need to obtain the latest status information about a
  particular host or service. For example, when &name-icinga; is determining the <link
  linkend="networkreachability">reachability</link> of a host, it will often perform on-demand checks of parent and child hosts to
  accurately determine the status of a particular network segment. On-demand checks also occur in the <link
  linkend="dependencychecks">predictive dependency check</link> logic in order to ensure &name-icinga; has the most accurate
  status information.</para>
  <indexterm zone="active_checks"><primary>Active Checks</primary><secondary>at regular intervals</secondary></indexterm>
  <indexterm zone="active_checks"><primary>Active Checks</primary><secondary>on demand</secondary></indexterm>
</section>
