<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="beginners" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="advice_for_beginners" />Advice for beginners</title>

  <para>Thanks for choosing &name-icinga;! &name-icinga; is quite powerful and flexible and although you can see the first results
  in less than 30 minutes, this is just the beginning of your journey into system monitoring. Configuring it to your needs can
  take a lot of work depending on the number of things to be monitored and the complexity of your environment. Once you become
  familiar with how it works and what it can do for you, you'll never want to be without it. :-) Here are some important things to
  keep in mind for first-time &name-icinga; users: <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Relax - it's going to take some time. Don't expect to be able to get things working exactly the way you want them
        right off the bat. It's not that easy. Setting up &name-icinga; can involve a bit of work - partly because of the options
        that &name-icinga; offers, partly because you need to know what to monitor on your network (and how best to do it)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Please use the <link linkend="quickstart">quickstart</link> instructions. The quickstart installation guide is
        designed to get most new users up and running with a basic &name-icinga; setup fairly quickly. Within 20 minutes you can
        have &name-icinga; installed and monitoring your local system. Once that's complete, you can move on to learning how to
        configure &name-icinga; to do more.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Read the documentation. &name-icinga; can be tricky to configure when you've got a good grasp of what's going on,
        and nearly impossible if you don't. Make sure you read the documentation (particularly the sections on <link
        linkend="ch03">"Configuring &name-icinga;"</link> and <link linkend="ch05">"The Basics"</link>). Save the <link
        linkend="ch06">advanced topics</link> for when you've got a good understanding of the basics.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Seek the help of others. If you've read the documentation, reviewed the sample config files, and are still having
        problems, send an email message describing your problems to the icinga-users mailing list. If you've done some background
        reading and you provide a good problem description, odds are that someone will give you some pointers on getting things
        working properly. "good description" means to include details on your operating system, the version of &name-icinga;, as
        well as what you tried and the results of it (preferably copy&amp;paste). More information on subscribing to the mailing
        lists or searching the list archives can be found at <link
        xlink:href="http://www.icinga.org/community/">&url-icingalists;</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist></para>
  <indexterm zone="advice_for_beginners"><primary>Beginners, Advice for</primary></indexterm>
</section>
