<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="clusters" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="monitoring_clusters" />Monitoring Service and Host Clusters</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>Several people have asked how to go about monitoring clusters of hosts or services, so this little documentation should
  provide you with some information on how to do this. It's fairly straightforward, so hopefully you find things easy to
  understand...</para>

  <para>First off, we need to define what we mean by a "cluster". The simplest way to understand this is with an example. Let's
  say that your organization has five hosts which provide redundant DNS services to your organization. If one of them fails, its
  not a major catastrophe because the remaining servers will continue to provide name resolution services. If you're concerned
  with monitoring the availability of DNS service to your organization, you will want to monitor five DNS servers. This is what is
  considered to be a <emphasis>service</emphasis> cluster. The service cluster consists of five separate DNS services that you are
  monitoring. Although you do want to monitor each individual service, your main concern is with the overall status of the DNS
  service cluster, rather than the availability of any one particular service.</para>

  <para>If your organization has a group of hosts that provide a high-availability (clustering) solution, that would be considered
  to be a <emphasis>host</emphasis> cluster. If one particular host fails, another will step in to take over all the duties of the
  failed server. As a side note, check out the <link xlink:href="http://www.linux-ha.org">High-Availability Linux Project</link>
  for information on providing host and service redundancy with Linux.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Plan of Attack</emphasis></para>

  <para>There are several ways you could potentially monitor service or host clusters. We'll describe one method to do that.
  Monitoring service or host clusters involves two things:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Monitoring individual cluster elements</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Monitoring the cluster as a collective entity</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Monitoring individual host or service cluster elements is easier than you think. In fact, you're probably already doing
  it. For service clusters, just make sure that you are monitoring each service element of the cluster. If you've got a cluster of
  five DNS servers, make sure you have five separate service definitions (probably using the <emphasis>check_dns</emphasis>
  plugin). For host clusters, make sure you have configured appropriate host definitions for each member of the cluster (you'll
  also have to define at least one service to be monitored for each of the hosts). <emphasis role="bold">Important:</emphasis>
  You're going to want to disable notifications for the individual cluster elements (host or service definitions). Even though no
  notifications will be sent about the individual elements, you'll still get a visual display of the individual host or service
  status in the <link linkend="cgis-status_cgi">status CGI</link>. This will be useful for pinpointing the source of problems
  within the cluster in the future.</para>

  <para>Monitoring the overall cluster can be done by using the previously cached results of cluster elements. Although you could
  re-check all elements of the cluster to determine the cluster's status, why waste bandwidth and resources when you already have
  the results cached? Where are the results cached? Cached results for cluster elements can be found in the <link
  linkend="configmain-status_file">status file</link> (assuming you are monitoring each element). The
  <emphasis>check_cluster</emphasis> plugin is designed specifically for checking cached host and service states in the status
  file. <emphasis role="bold">Important:</emphasis> Although you didn't enable notifications for individual elements of the
  cluster, you will want them enabled for the overall cluster status check.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Using the check_cluster Plugin</emphasis></para>

  <para>The check_cluster plugin is designed to report the overall status of a host or service cluster by checking the status
  information of each individual host or service cluster elements.</para>

  <para>More to come... The <emphasis>check_cluster</emphasis> plugin can be found in the contrib directory of the &name-nagios;
  Plugins release at <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/nagiosplug">&url-nagiosplug-sf;</link>.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring Service Clusters</emphasis></para>

  <para>Let's say you have three DNS servers that provide redundant services on your network. First off, you need to be monitoring
  each of these DNS servers separately before you can monitor them as a cluster. We'll assume that you already have three separate
  services (all called "DNS Service") associated with your DNS hosts (called "host1", "host2" and "host3").</para>

  <para>In order to monitor the services as a cluster, you'll need to create a new "cluster" service. However, before you do that,
  make sure you have a service cluster check command configured. Let's assume that you have a command called
  <emphasis>check_service_cluster</emphasis> defined as follows:</para>

  <screen> define command{
        command_name    check_service_cluster
        command_line    &url-icinga-base;/libexec/check_cluster --service -l $ARG1$ -w $ARG2$ -c $ARG3$ -d $ARG4$ 
        }</screen>

  <para>Now you'll need to create the "cluster" service and use the <emphasis>check_service_cluster</emphasis> command you just
  created as the cluster's check command. The example below gives an example of how to do this. The example below will generate a
  CRITICAL alert if 2 or more services in the cluster are in a non-OK state, and a WARNING alert if only 1 of the services is in a
  non-OK state. If all the individual service members of the cluster are OK, the cluster check will return an OK state as
  well.</para>

  <screen> define service{
        ...
        check_command   check_service_cluster!"DNS Cluster"!0!1!$SERVICESTATEID:host1:DNS Service$,$SERVICESTATEID:host2:DNS Service$,$SERVICESTATEID:host3:DNS Service$
        ...
        }</screen>

  <para>It is important to notice that we are passing a comma-delimited list of <emphasis>on-demand</emphasis> service state <link
  linkend="macros">macros</link> to the $ARG4$ macro in the cluster check command. That's important! &name-icinga; will fill those
  on-demand macros in with the current service state IDs (numerical values, rather than text strings) of the individual members of
  the cluster.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring Host Clusters</emphasis></para>

  <para>Monitoring host clusters is very similiar to monitoring service clusters. Obviously, the main difference is that the
  cluster members are hosts and not services. In order to monitor the status of a host cluster, you must define a service that
  uses the <emphasis>check_cluster</emphasis> plugin. The service should <emphasis>not</emphasis> be associated with any of the
  hosts in the cluster, as this will cause problems with notifications for the cluster if that host goes down. A good idea might
  be to associate the service with the host that &name-icinga; is running on. After all, if the host that &name-icinga; is running
  on goes down, then &name-icinga; isn't running anymore, so there isn't anything you can do as far as monitoring (unless you've
  setup <link linkend="redundancy">redundant monitoring hosts</link>)...</para>

  <para>Anyway, let's assume that you have a <emphasis>check_host_cluster</emphasis> command defined as follows:</para>

  <screen> define command{
        command_name    check_host_cluster
        command_line    &url-icinga-base;/libexec/check_cluster --host -l $ARG1$ -w $ARG2$ -c $ARG3$ -d $ARG4$ 
        }</screen>

  <para>Let's say you have three hosts (named "host1", "host2" and "host3") in the host cluster. If you want &name-icinga; to
  generate a warning alert if one host in the cluster is not UP or a critical alert if two or more hosts are not UP, the the
  service you define to monitor the host cluster might look something like this:</para>

  <screen> define service{
        ...
        check_command   check_host_cluster!"Super Host Cluster"!0!1!$HOSTSTATEID:host1$,$HOSTSTATEID:host2$,$HOSTSTATEID:host3$
        ...
        }</screen>

  <para>It is important to notice that we are passing a comma-delimited list of <emphasis>on-demand</emphasis> host state <link
  linkend="macros">macros</link> to the $ARG4$ macro in the cluster check command. That's important! &name-icinga; will fill those
  on-demand macros in with the current host state IDs (numerical values, rather than text strings) of the individual members of
  the cluster.</para>

  <para>That's it! &name-icinga; will periodically check the status of the host cluster and send notifications to you when its
  status is degraded (assuming you've enabled notification for the service). Note that for thehost definitions of each cluster
  member, you will most likely want to disable notifications when the host goes down . Remeber that you don't care as much about
  the status of any individual host as you do the overall status of the cluster. Depending on your network layout and what you're
  trying to accomplish, you may wish to leave notifications for unreachable states enabled for the host definitions.</para>
  <indexterm zone="monitoring_clusters"><primary>Cluster</primary><secondary>Monitoring Service and Host Clusters</secondary></indexterm>
</section>
