<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="downtime" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="schedule_downtime" />Scheduled Downtime</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>&name-icinga; allows you to schedule periods of planned downtime for hosts and service that you're monitoring. This is
  useful in the event that you actually know you're going to be taking a server down for an upgrade, etc.</para>

  <para><inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/downtime.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject></para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Scheduling Downtime</emphasis></para>

  <para>You can schedule downtime for hosts and service through the <link linkend="cgis-extinfo_cgi">extinfo CGI</link> (either
  when viewing host or service information). Click in the "Schedule downtime for this host/service" link to actually schedule the
  downtime.</para>

  <para>Once you schedule downtime for a host or service, &name-icinga; will add a comment to that host/service indicating that it
  is scheduled for downtime during the period of time you indicated. When that period of downtime passes, &name-icinga; will
  automatically delete the comment that it added. Nice, huh?</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Fixed vs. Flexible Downtime</emphasis></para>

  <para>When you schedule downtime for a host or service through the web interface you'll be asked if the downtime is fixed or
  flexible. Here's an explanation of how "fixed" and "flexible" downtime differs:</para>

  <para>"Fixed" downtime starts and stops at the exact start and end times that you specify when you schedule it. Okay, that was
  easy enough...</para>

  <para>"Flexible" downtime is intended for times when you know that a host or service is going to be down for X minutes (or
  hours), but you don't know exactly when that'll start. When you schedule flexible downtime, &name-icinga; will start the
  scheduled downtime sometime between the start and end times you specified. The downtime will last for as long as the duration
  you specified when you scheduled the downtime. This assumes that the host or service for which you scheduled flexible downtime
  either goes down (or becomes unreachable) or goes into a non-OK state sometime between the start and end times you specified.
  The time at which a host or service transitions to a problem state determines the time at which &name-icinga; actually starts
  the downtime. The downtime will then last for the duration you specified, even if the host or service recovers before the
  downtime expires. This is done for a very good reason. As we all know, you might think you've got a problem fixed, but then have
  to restart a server ten times before it actually works right. Smart, eh?</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Triggered Downtime</emphasis></para>

  <para>When scheduling host or service downtime you have the option of making it "triggered" downtime. What is triggered
  downtime, you ask? With triggered downtime the start of the downtime is triggered by the start of some other scheduled host or
  service downtime. This is extremely useful if you're scheduling downtime for a large number or hosts or services and the start
  time of the downtime period depends on the start time of another downtime entry. For instance, if you schedule flexible downtime
  for a particular host (because its going down for maintenance), you might want to schedule triggered downtime for all of that
  hosts's "children".</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">How Scheduled Downtime Affects Notifications</emphasis></para>

  <para>When a host or service is in a period of scheduled downtime, &name-icinga; will not allow normal notifications to be sent
  out for the host or service. However, a "DOWNTIMESTART" notification will get sent out for the host or service, which will serve
  to put any admins on notice that they won't receive upcoming problem alerts.</para>

  <para>When the scheduled downtime is over, &name-icinga; will allow normal notifications to be sent out for the host or service
  again. A "DOWNTIMEEND" notification will get sent out notifying admins that the scheduled downtime is over, and they will start
  receiving normal alerts again.</para>

  <para>If the scheduled downtime is cancelled prematurely (before it expires), a "DOWNTIMECANCELLED" notification will get sent
  out to the appropriate admins.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Overlapping Scheduled Downtime</emphasis></para>

  <para>I like to refer to this as the "Oh crap, its not working" syndrome. You know what I'm talking about. You take a server
  down to perform a "routine" hardware upgrade, only to later realize that the OS drivers aren't working, the RAID array blew up,
  or the drive imaging failed and left your original disks useless to the world. Moral of the story is that any routine work on a
  server is quite likely to take three or four times as long as you had originally planned...</para>

  <para>Let's take the following scenario:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>You schedule downtime for host A from 7:30pm-9:30pm on a Monday</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>You bring the server down about 7:45pm Monday evening to start a hard drive upgrade</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>After wasting an hour and a half battling with SCSI errors and driver incompatibilities, you finally get the machine
      to boot up</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>At 9:15 you realize that one of your partitions is either hosed or doesn't seem to exist anywhere on the drive</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Knowing you're in for a long night, you go back and schedule additional downtime for host A from 9:20pm Monday evening
      to 1:30am Tuesday Morning.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>If you schedule overlapping periods of downtime for a host or service (in this case the periods were 7:40pm-9:30pm and
  9:20pm-1:30am), &name-icinga; will wait until the last period of scheduled downtime is over before it allows notifications to be
  sent out for that host or service. In this example notifications would be suppressed for host A until 1:30am Tuesday
  morning.</para>
  <indexterm zone="schedule_downtime"><primary>Downtime</primary><secondary>scheduled</secondary></indexterm>
</section>
