<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="icinga-overview" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>&name-icinga; Overview</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold"><anchor xml:id="icinga_overview"/>Overview</emphasis></para>

  <para>This section should give you a short overview on what is included and what isn't. It might be incomplete but we're working on
  that.</para>

  <para>&name-icinga; consists of a core processing results from checks which are initiated by the core (<link linkend="activechecks">active
  checks</link>), or delivered from other machines (<link linkend="passivechecks">passive checks</link>), deciding if <link
  linkend="notifications">notifications</link> have to be sent, providing information by writing log files and showing it via a <link
  linkend="cgis">web interface</link>, and several other tasks.</para>

  <para>The core does <emphasis>not</emphasis> contain any checks itself but they are executed by <link linkend="plugins">plugins</link>
  instead. Notifying <link linkend="objectdefinitions-contact">contacts</link> is done by methods provided by the operating system (i.e.
  sendmail/postfix/..., sms, pager). <note>
      <para>Installation and configuration of plugins, addons, and os related software is mostly beyond the scope of this documentation so
      please consult the documentation provided by the manufacturer first, use your favourite search engine if that doesn't help, and seek
      help in forums. Consulting instructions from blogs or other personal stuff you will often find information that is outdated or doesn't
      fit your environment so try to avoid such sources.</para>
    </note>Extending the functionality can be accomplished by installing <link linkend="addons">addons</link>. There you will find hints on
  web-based configuration tools, alternative web interfaces, presenting performance data, notifying contacts, and more.</para>

  <para>The configuration is based on text files and managing them requires just a text editor like vi. <link
  linkend="objectinheritance">Inheritance</link> using templates simplifies defining objects because it enables you to reduce the definition
  to a minimum.</para>

  <para>Accessing the information can be done via the cgi-based classic ui, the &name-web; ui, or several other interfaces like mentioned in
  <link linkend="addons">addons</link> as well.</para>
</section>
