<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="monitoring-overview" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="monitoring_overview"/>Monitoring Overview</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>&name-icinga; is intended to monitor devices (e.g. server, router, printer, and other hardware like temperature sensors) and
  services (processes running on these devices, metrics, etc.). There are several ways to do that and different approaches for different
  devices depending on your needs or the infrastructure.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="activechecks">Active checks</link></para>

      <para>The checks are initiated from the monitoring server repeated at given intervals. The server is waiting for the check results.
      The values and thresholds are set on the monitoring server. Check results can be retrieved</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>using SNMP. The remote system runs an SNMP daemon allowing to read the requested values. Depending on the plugin and the
          daemon SNMP v1, v2c, or v3 are supported</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>using <link linkend="nrpe">NRPE</link>, calling an NRPE daemon on the remote system which executes a check and returns the
          results to NRPE which in turn delivers it to the &name-icinga; process</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>calling a plugin using SSH to call a check on the remote system which returns the data to the plugin</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>using the plugin check_nt to connect to a service (e.g. "<link xlink:href="http://nsclient.org">NSClient++</link>") on the
          remote windows box and return data on several metrics</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>using addons like <link xlink:href="http://my-plugin.de">check_multi</link> or <link
          xlink:href="http://mathias-kettner.de/check_mk_overview.html">check_mk</link> which call plugins on their own to decrease the
          performance impact on the monitoring process (due to parallel calls). The configuration of values and thresholds is mostly moved
          to these addons which might increase the time of administration</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="passivechecks">Passive checks</link></para>

      <para>The checks are initiated on remote systems (not necessarily the system to be monitored but probably "satellite systems", aka
      "pollers", which monitor an organisational unit). The check results are transmitted to the monitoring server using <link
      linkend="nsca">NSCA</link> consisting of send_nsca on the client system and the nsca daemon on the monitoring server and processed
      there to update the current status. Setting <link linkend="freshness">freshness thresholds</link> will notify you if results do not
      appear in time. Depending on the configuration tools used administration might be more complex but using firewalls or other
      limitations imposed by security, customers, and/or other means you might not have the choice. Using passive checks will decrease the
      load on your monitoring system, too, because it only has to process the check results instead of executing checks itself. You can use
      entries in the crontab to execute checks at fixed times, execute long running queries when necessary or execute backup jobs returning
      only the results.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><!--<link xlink:href="http://www.teamix.org/projects/nagixsc">-->A mix of both<!--</link>--></para>

      <para>You might have remote systems running checks at given intervals providing data via a secret and secure page on a web server. The
      monitoring server is not able to check the systems directly (due to firewalls, customer regulations, etc.) but can access the document
      provided by the web server. It will retrieve the data using scripts (checks?) and injecting the results via <link
      linkend="extcommands">external commands</link>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>SNMP-Traps</para>

      <para>Sometimes you don't want to check things periodically because they are running smoothly and it would impose unnecessary network
      load. Several devices will inform you themselves when something goes wrong by using SNMP traps.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <indexterm zone="adaptive_monitoring">
    <primary>Monitoring Overview</primary>
  </indexterm>
</section>
