<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="monitoring-publicservices" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="monitoring_publicservices" />Monitoring Publicly Available Services</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>This document describes how you can monitor publicly available services, applications and protocols. By "public" we mean
  services that are accessible across the network - either the local network or the greater Internet. Examples of public services
  include HTTP, POP3, IMAP, FTP, and SSH. There are many more public services that you probably use on a daily basis. These
  services and applications, as well as their underlying protocols, can usually be monitored by &name-icinga; without any special
  access requirements.</para>

  <para>Private services, in contrast, cannot be monitored with &name-icinga; without an intermediary agent of some kind. Examples
  of private services associated with hosts are things like CPU load, memory usage, disk usage, current user count, process
  information, etc. These private services or attributes of hosts are not usually exposed to external clients. This situation
  requires that an intermediary monitoring agent be installed on any host that you need to monitor such information on. More
  information on monitoring private services on different types of hosts can be found in the documentation on:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="monitoring-windows">Monitoring Windows machines</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="monitoring-netware">Monitoring Netware servers</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link linkend="monitoring-linux">Monitoring Linux/Unix machines</link></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <tip>
    <para>Occasionally you will find that information on private services and applications can be monitored with SNMP. The SNMP
    agent allows you to remotely monitor otherwise private (and inaccessible) information about the host. For more information
    about monitoring services using SNMP, check out the documentation on <link linkend="monitoring-routers">monitoring switches
    and routers</link>.</para>
  </tip>

  <note>
    <para>These instructions assume that you've installed &name-icinga; according to the <link linkend="quickstart">quickstart
    guide</link>. The sample configuration entries below reference objects that are defined in the sample
    <emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis> and <emphasis>localhost.cfg</emphasis> config files.</para>
  </note>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Plugins for Monitoring Services</emphasis></para>

  <para>When you find yourself needing to monitor a particular application, service, or protocol, chances are good that a <link
  linkend="plugins">plugin</link> exists to monitor it. The official Nagios plugins distribution comes with plugins that can be
  used to monitor a variety of services and protocols. There are also a large number of contributed plugins that can be found in
  the <emphasis>contrib/</emphasis> subdirectory of the plugin distribution. The <link
  xlink:href="http://www.monitoringexchange.org">MonitoringExchange.org</link> website hosts a number of additional plugins that
  have been written by users, so check it out when you have a chance.</para>

  <para>If you don't happen to find an appropriate plugin for monitoring what you need, you can always write your own. Plugins are
  easy to write, so don't let this thought scare you off. Read the documentation on <link linkend="pluginapi">developing
  plugins</link> for more information.</para>

  <para>We'll walk you through monitoring some basic services that you'll probably use sooner or later. Each of these services can
  be monitored using one of the plugins that gets installed as part of the Nagios plugins distribution. Let's get
  started...</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Creating a Host Definition</emphasis></para>

  <para>Before you can monitor a service, you first need to define a <link linkend="objectdefinitions-host">host</link> that is
  associated with the service. You can place host definitions in any object configuration file specified by a <link
  linkend="configmain-cfg_file">cfg_file</link> directive or placed in a directory specified by a <link
  linkend="configmain-cfg_dir">cfg_dir</link> directive. If you have already created a host definition, you can skip this
  step.</para>

  <para>For this example, lets say you want to monitor a variety of services on a remote host. Let's call that host
  <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis>. The host definition can be placed in its own file or added to an already exiting object
  configuration file. Here's what the host definition for <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis> might look like:</para>

  <screen> define host{
        use             generic-host            ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name       remotehost              ; The name we're giving to this host
        alias           Some Remote Host        ; A longer name associated with the host
        address         192.168.1.50            ; IP address of the host
        hostgroups      allhosts                ; Host groups this host is associated with
        }</screen>

  <para>Now that a definition has been added for the host that will be monitored, we can start defining services that should be
  monitored. As with host definitions, service definitions can be placed in any object configuration file.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Creating Service Definitions</emphasis></para>

  <para>For each service you want to monitor, you need to define a <link linkend="objectdefinitions-service">service</link> in
  &name-icinga; that is associated with the host definition you just created. You can place service definitions in any object
  configuration file specified by a <link linkend="configmain-cfg_file">cfg_file</link> directive or placed in a directory
  specified by a <link linkend="configmain-cfg_dir">cfg_dir</link> directive.</para>

  <para>Some example service definitions for monitoring common public service (HTTP, FTP, etc) are given below.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring HTTP</emphasis></para>

  <para>Chances are you're going to want to monitor web servers at some point - either yours or someone else's. The
  <emphasis>check_http</emphasis> plugin is designed to do just that. It understands the HTTP protocol and can monitor response
  time, error codes, strings in the returned HTML, server certificates, and much more.</para>

  <para>The <emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis> file contains a command definition for using the <emphasis>check_http</emphasis>
  plugin. It looks like this:</para>

  <screen> define command{
        name            check_http
        command_name    check_http
        command_line    $USER1$/check_http -I $HOSTADDRESS$ $ARG1$
        }</screen>

  <para>A simple service definition for monitoring the HTTP service on the <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis> machine might look like
  this:</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     HTTP
        check_command           check_http
        }</screen>

  <para>This simple service definition will monitor the HTTP service running on <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis>. It will produce
  alerts if the web server doesn't respond within 10 seconds or if it returns HTTP errors codes (403, 404, etc.). That's all you
  need for basic monitoring. Pretty simple, huh?</para>

  <tip>
    <para>For more advanced monitoring, run the <emphasis>check_http</emphasis> plugin manually with <emphasis>--help</emphasis>
    as a command-line argument to see all the options you can give the plugin. This <emphasis>--help</emphasis> syntax works with
    all of the plugins we'll cover in this document.</para>
  </tip>

  <para>A more advanced definition for monitoring the HTTP service is shown below. This service definition will check to see if
  the /download/index.php URI contains the string "latest-version.tar.gz". It will produce an error if the string isn't found, the
  URI isn't valid, or the web server takes longer than 5 seconds to respond.</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     Product Download Link
        check_command           check_http!-u /download/index.php -t 5 -s "latest-version.tar.gz"
        }</screen>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring FTP</emphasis></para>

  <para>When you need to monitor FTP servers, you can use the <emphasis>check_ftp</emphasis> plugin. The
  <emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis> file contains a command definition for using the <emphasis>check_ftp</emphasis> plugin, which
  looks like this:</para>

  <screen> define command{
        command_name    check_ftp
        command_line    $USER1$/check_ftp -H $HOSTADDRESS$ $ARG1$
        }</screen>

  <para>A simple service definition for monitoring the FTP server on <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis> would look like this:</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     FTP
        check_command           check_ftp
        }</screen>

  <para>This service definition will monitor the FTP service and generate alerts if the FTP server doesn't respond within 10
  seconds.</para>

  <para>A more advanced service definition is shown below. This service will check the FTP server running on port 1023 on
  <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis>. It will generate an alert if the server doesn't respond within 5 seconds or if the server
  response doesn't contain the string "Pure-FTPd [TLS]".</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     Special FTP 
        check_command           check_ftp!-p 1023 -t 5 -e "Pure-FTPd [TLS]"
        }</screen>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring SSH</emphasis></para>

  <para>When you need to monitor SSH servers, you can use the <emphasis>check_ssh</emphasis> plugin. The
  <emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis> file contains a command definition for using the <emphasis>check_ssh</emphasis> plugin, which
  looks like this:</para>

  <screen> define command{
        command_name    check_ssh
        command_line    $USER1$/check_ssh $ARG1$ $HOSTADDRESS$
        }</screen>

  <para>A simple service definition for monitoring the SSH server on <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis> would look like this:</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     SSH
        check_command           check_ssh
        }</screen>

  <para>This service definition will monitor the SSH service and generate alerts if the SSH server doesn't respond within 10
  seconds.</para>

  <para>A more advanced service definition is shown below. This service will check the SSH server and generate an alert if the
  server doesn't respond within 5 seconds or if the server version string string doesn't match "OpenSSH_4.2".</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     SSH Version Check 
        check_command           check_ssh!-t 5 -r "OpenSSH_4.2"
        }</screen>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring SMTP</emphasis></para>

  <para>The <emphasis>check_smtp</emphasis> plugin can be using for monitoring your email servers. The
  <emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis> file contains a command definition for using the <emphasis>check_smtp</emphasis> plugin, which
  looks like this:</para>

  <screen> define command{
        command_name    check_smtp
        command_line    $USER1$/check_smtp -H $HOSTADDRESS$ $ARG1$
        }</screen>

  <para>A simple service definition for monitoring the SMTP server on <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis> would look like this:</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     SMTP
        check_command           check_smtp
        }</screen>

  <para>This service definition will monitor the SMTP service and generate alerts if the SMTP server doesn't respond within 10
  seconds.</para>

  <para>A more advanced service definition is shown below. This service will check the SMTP server and generate an alert if the
  server doesn't respond within 5 seconds or if the response from the server doesn't contain "mygreatmailserver.com".</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     SMTP Response Check 
        check_command           check_smtp!-t 5 -e "mygreatmailserver.com"
        }</screen>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring POP3</emphasis></para>

  <para>The <emphasis>check_pop</emphasis> plugin can be using for monitoring the POP3 service on your email servers. The
  <emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis> file contains a command definition for using the <emphasis>check_pop</emphasis> plugin, which
  looks like this:</para>

  <screen> define command{
        command_name    check_pop
        command_line    $USER1$/check_pop -H $HOSTADDRESS$ $ARG1$
        }</screen>

  <para>A simple service definition for monitoring the POP3 service on <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis> would look like
  this:</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     POP3
        check_command           check_pop
        }</screen>

  <para>This service definition will monitor the POP3 service and generate alerts if the POP3 server doesn't respond within 10
  seconds.</para>

  <para>A more advanced service definition is shown below. This service will check the POP3 service and generate an alert if the
  server doesn't respond within 5 seconds or if the response from the server doesn't contain "mygreatmailserver.com".</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     POP3 Response Check 
        check_command           check_pop!-t 5 -e "mygreatmailserver.com"
        }</screen>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Monitoring IMAP</emphasis></para>

  <para>The <emphasis>check_imap</emphasis> plugin can be using for monitoring IMAP4 service on your email servers. The
  <emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis> file contains a command definition for using the <emphasis>check_imap</emphasis> plugin, which
  looks like this:</para>

  <screen> define command{
        command_name    check_imap
        command_line    $USER1$/check_imap -H $HOSTADDRESS$ $ARG1$
        }</screen>

  <para>A simple service definition for monitoring the IMAP4 service on <emphasis>remotehost</emphasis> would look like
  this:</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     IMAP
        check_command           check_imap
        }</screen>

  <para>This service definition will monitor the IMAP4 service and generate alerts if the IMAP server doesn't respond within 10
  seconds.</para>

  <para>A more advanced service definition is shown below. This service will check the IAMP4 service and generate an alert if the
  server doesn't respond within 5 seconds or if the response from the server doesn't contain "mygreatmailserver.com".</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name               remotehost
        service_description     IMAP4 Response Check 
        check_command           check_imap!-t 5 -e "mygreatmailserver.com"
        }
</screen>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Restarting &name-icinga;</emphasis></para>

  <para>Once you've added the new host and service definitions to your object configuration file(s), you're ready to start
  monitoring them. To do this, you'll need to <link linkend="verifyconfig">verify your configuration</link> and <link
  linkend="startstop">restart &name-icinga;</link>.</para>

  <para>If the verification process produces any errors messages, fix your configuration file before continuing. Make sure that
  you don't (re)start &name-icinga; until the verification process completes without any errors!</para>
  <indexterm zone="monitoring_publicservices"><primary>Monitoring</primary><secondary>Monitoring Publicly Available Services</secondary></indexterm>
</section>
