<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="monitoring-printers" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="monitoring_printers" />Monitoring Network Printers</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para><informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/printer.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure></para>

  <para>This document describes how you can monitor the status of networked printers. Specifically, HP printers that have
  internal/external JetDirect cards/devices, or other print servers (like the Troy PocketPro 100S or the Netgear PS101) that
  support the JetDirect protocol.</para>

  <para>The <emphasis>check_hpjd</emphasis> plugin (which is part of the standard &name-nagios; plugins distribution) allows you
  to monitor the status of JetDirect-capable printers which have SNMP enabled. The plugin is capable of detecting the following
  printer states:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Paper Jam</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Out of Paper</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Printer Offline</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Intervention Required</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Toner Low</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Insufficient Memory</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Open Door</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Output Tray is Full</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>and more...</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <note>
    <para>These instructions assume that you've installed &name-icinga; according to the <link linkend="quickstart">quickstart
    guide</link>. The sample configuration entries below reference objects that are defined in the sample config files
    (<emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis>, <emphasis>templates.cfg</emphasis>, etc.) that are installed if you follow the
    quickstart.</para>
  </note>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Overview</emphasis></para>

  <para><informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/monitoring-printers.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure></para>

  <para>Monitoring the status of a networked printer is pretty simple. JetDirect-enabled printers usually have SNMP enabled, which
  allows &name-icinga; to monitor their status using the <emphasis>check_hpjd</emphasis> plugin.</para>

  <para>The <emphasis>check_hpjd</emphasis> plugin will only get compiled and installed if you have the net-snmp and
  net-snmp-utils packages installed on your system. Make sure the plugin exists in <emphasis>&url-icinga-base;/libexec</emphasis>
  before you continue. If it doesn't, install net-snmp and net-snmp-utils and recompile/reinstall the &name-nagios;
  plugins.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Steps</emphasis></para>

  <para>There are several steps you'll need to follow in order to monitor a new network printer. They are:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Perform first-time prerequisites</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Create new host and service definitions for monitoring the printer</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Restart the &name-icinga; daemon</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">What's Already Done For You</emphasis></para>

  <para>To make your life a bit easier, a few configuration tasks have already been done for you:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>A <emphasis>check_hpjd</emphasis> command definition has been added to the <emphasis>commands.cfg</emphasis> file.
      This allows you to use the <emphasis>check_hpjd</emphasis> plugin to monitor network printers.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A printer host template (called <emphasis>generic-printer</emphasis>) has already been created in the
      <emphasis>templates.cfg</emphasis> file. This allows you to add new printer host definitions in a simple manner.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The above-mentioned config files can be found in the <emphasis>&url-icinga-base;/etc/objects/</emphasis> directory. You
  can modify the definitions in these and other definitions to suit your needs better if you'd like. However, we'd recommend
  waiting until you're more familiar with configuring &name-icinga; before doing so. For the time being, just follow the
  directions outlined below and you'll be monitoring your network printers in no time.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Prerequisites</emphasis></para>

  <para>The first time you configure &name-icinga; to monitor a network printer, you'll need to do a bit of extra work. Remember,
  you only need to do this for the *first* printer you monitor.</para>

  <para>Edit the main &name-icinga; config file.</para>

  <screen># vi &url-icinga-cfg;</screen>

  <para>Remove the leading hash (#) sign from the following line in the main configuration file:</para>

  <screen> #cfg_file=&url-icinga-base;/etc/objects/printer.cfg</screen>

  <para>Save the file and exit.</para>

  <para>What did you just do? You told &name-icinga; to look to the <emphasis>&url-icinga-base;/etc/objects/printer.cfg</emphasis>
  to find additional object definitions. That's where you'll be adding host and service definitions for the printer. That
  configuration file already contains some sample host, hostgroup, and service definitions. For the *first* printer you monitor,
  you can simply modify the sample host and service definitions in that file, rather than creating new ones.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Configuring &name-icinga;</emphasis></para>

  <para>You'll need to create some <link linkend="objectdefinitions">object definitions</link> in order to monitor a new
  printer.</para>

  <para>Open the <emphasis>printer.cfg</emphasis> file for editing.</para>

  <screen> vi &url-icinga-base;/etc/objects/printer.cfg</screen>

  <para>Add a new <link linkend="objectdefinitions-host">host</link> definition for the networked printer that you're going to
  monitor. If this is the *first* printer you're monitoring, you can simply modify the sample host definition in
  <emphasis>printer.cfg</emphasis>. Change the <emphasis>host_name</emphasis>, <emphasis>alias</emphasis>, and
  <emphasis>address</emphasis> fields to appropriate values for the printer.</para>

  <screen> define host{
        use             generic-printer ; Inherit default values from a template
        host_name       hplj2605dn      ; The name we're giving to this printer
        alias           HP LaserJet 2605dn      ; A longer name associated with the printer
        address         192.168.1.30    ; IP address of the printer
        hostgroups      allhosts                ; Host groups this printer is associated with
        } </screen>

  <para>Now you can add some service definitions (to the same configuration file) to monitor different aspects of the printer. If
  this is the *first* printer you're monitoring, you can simply modify the sample service definition in
  <emphasis>printer.cfg</emphasis>.</para>

  <note>
    <para>Replace "<emphasis>hplj2605dn</emphasis>" in the example definitions below with the name you specified in the
    <emphasis>host_name</emphasis> directive of the host definition you just added.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Add the following service definition to check the status of the printer. The service uses the
  <emphasis>check_hpjd</emphasis> plugin to check the status of the printer every 10 minutes by default. The SNMP community string
  used to query the printer is "public" in this example.</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service         ; Inherit values from a template
        host_name               hplj2605dn              ; The name of the host the service is associated with
        service_description     Printer Status          ; The service description
        check_command           check_hpjd!-C public    ; The command used to monitor the service
        check_interval          10      ; Check the service every 10 minutes under normal conditions
        retry_interval          1       ; Re-check the service every minute until its final/hard state is determined
        }</screen>

  <para>Add the following service definition to ping the printer every 10 minutes by default. This is useful for monitoring RTA,
  packet loss, and general network connectivity.</para>

  <screen> define service{
        use                     generic-service
        host_name               hplj2605dn
        service_description     PING
        check_command           check_ping!3000.0,80%!5000.0,100%
        check_interval          10
        retry_interval          1
        }</screen>

  <para>Save the file.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Restarting &name-icinga;</emphasis></para>

  <para>Once you've added the new host and service definitions to the <emphasis>printer.cfg</emphasis> file, you're ready to start
  monitoring the printer. To do this, you'll need to <link linkend="verifyconfig">verify your configuration</link> and <link
  linkend="startstop">restart &name-icinga;</link>.</para>

  <para>If the verification process produces any errors messages, fix your configuration file before continuing. Make sure that
  you don't (re)start &name-icinga; until the verification process completes without any errors!</para>
  <indexterm zone="monitoring_printers"><primary>Monitoring</primary><secondary>Monitoring Network Printers</secondary></indexterm>
</section>
