<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="notifications" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="explanation_notifications" />Notifications</title>

  <para><inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/objects-contacts.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject></para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>I've had a lot of questions as to exactly how notifications work. This will attempt to explain exactly when and how host and service
  notifications are sent out, as well as who receives them.</para>

  <para>Notification escalations are explained <link linkend="escalations">here</link>.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">When Do Notifications Occur?</emphasis></para>

  <para>The decision to send out notifications is made in the service check and host check logic. The calculations for whether a
  notification is to be sent are only triggered when processing a host or service check corresponding to that notification; they are not
  triggered simply because the &lt;notification_interval&gt; has passed since a previous notification was sent. Host and service
  notifications occur in the following instances...</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>When a hard state change occurs. More information on state types and hard state changes can be found <link
      linkend="statetypes">here</link>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>When a host or service remains in a hard non-OK state and the time specified by the
      &lt;<emphasis>notification_interval</emphasis>&gt; option in the host or service definition has passed since the last notification was
      sent out (for that specified host or service).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Who Gets Notified?</emphasis></para>

  <para>Each host and service definition has a &lt;<emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis>&gt; option that specifies what contact groups receive
  notifications for that particular host or service. Contact groups can contain one or more individual contacts.</para>

  <para>When &name-icinga; sends out a host or service notification, it will notify each contact that is a member of any contact groups
  specified in the &lt;<emphasis>contactgroups</emphasis>&gt; option of the service definition. &name-icinga; realizes that a contact may be
  a member of more than one contact group, so it removes duplicate contact notifications before it does anything.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">What Filters Must Be Passed In Order For Notifications To Be Sent?</emphasis></para>

  <para>Just because there is a need to send out a host or service notification doesn't mean that any contacts are going to get notified.
  There are several filters that potential notifications must pass before they are deemed worthy enough to be sent out. Even then, specific
  contacts may not be notified if their notification filters do not allow for the notification to be sent to them. Let's go into the filters
  that have to be passed in more detail...</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Program-Wide Filter:</emphasis></para>

  <para>The first filter that notifications must pass is a test of whether or not notifications are enabled on a program-wide basis. This is
  initially determined by the <link linkend="configmain-enable_notifications">enable_notifications</link> directive in the main config file,
  but may be changed during runtime from the web interface. If notifications are disabled on a program-wide basis, no host or service
  notifications can be sent out - period. If they are enabled on a program-wide basis, there are still other tests that must be
  passed...</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Service and Host Filters:</emphasis></para>

  <para>The first filter for host or service notifications is a check to see if the host or service is in a period of <link
  linkend="downtime">scheduled downtime</link>. It it is in a scheduled downtime, <emphasis role="bold">no one gets notified</emphasis>. If
  it isn't in a period of downtime, it gets passed on to the next filter. As a side note, notifications for services are suppressed if the
  host they're associated with is in a period of scheduled downtime.</para>

  <para>The second filter for host or service notification is a check to see if the host or service is <link
  linkend="flapping">flapping</link> (if you enabled flap detection). If the service or host is currently flapping, <emphasis role="bold">no
  one gets notified</emphasis>. Otherwise it gets passed to the next filter.</para>

  <para>The third host or service filter that must be passed is the host- or service-specific notification options. Each service definition
  contains options that determine whether or not notifications can be sent out for warning states, critical states, and recoveries.
  Similiarly, each host definition contains options that determine whether or not notifications can be sent out when the host goes down,
  becomes unreachable, or recovers. If the host or service notification does not pass these options, <emphasis role="bold">no one gets
  notified</emphasis>. If it does pass these options, the notification gets passed to the next filter...</para>

  <note>
    <para>Notifications about host or service recoveries are only sent out if a notification was sent out for the original problem. It
    doesn't make sense to get a recovery notification for something you never knew was a problem.</para>
  </note>

  <para>The fourth host or service filter that must be passed is the time period test. Each host and service definition has a
  &lt;<emphasis>notification_period</emphasis>&gt; option that specifies which time period contains valid notification times for the host or
  service. If the time that the notification is being made does not fall within a valid time range in the specified time period, <emphasis
  role="bold">no one gets contacted</emphasis>. If it falls within a valid time range, the notification gets passed to the next
  filter...</para>

  <note>
    <para>If the time period filter is not passed, &name-icinga; will reschedule the next notification for the host or service (if its in a
    non-OK state) for the next valid time present in the time period. This helps ensure that contacts are notified of problems as soon as
    possible when the next valid time in time period arrives.</para>
  </note>

  <para>The last set of host or service filters is conditional upon two things: (1) a notification was already sent out about a problem with
  the host or service at some point in the past and (2) the host or service has remained in the same non-OK state that it was when the last
  notification went out. If these two criteria are met, then &name-icinga; will check and make sure the time that has passed since the last
  notification went out either meets or exceeds the value specified by the &lt;<emphasis>notification_interval</emphasis>&gt; option in the
  host or service definition. If not enough time has passed since the last notification, <emphasis role="bold">no one gets
  contacted</emphasis>. If either enough time has passed since the last notification or the two criteria for this filter were not met, the
  notification will be sent out! Whether or not it actually is sent to individual contacts is up to another set of filters...</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Contact Filters:</emphasis></para>

  <para>At this point the notification has passed the program mode filter and all host or service filters and &name-icinga; starts to notify
  <link linkend="objectdefinitions-contact">all the people it should</link>. Does this mean that each contact is going to receive the
  notification? No! Each contact has their own set of filters that the notification must pass before they receive it.</para>

  <note>
    <para>Contact filters are specific to each contact and do not affect whether or not other contacts receive notifications.</para>
  </note>

  <para>The first filter that must be passed for each contact are the notification options. Each contact definition contains options that
  determine whether or not service notifications can be sent out for warning states, critical states, and recoveries. Each contact
  definition also contains options that determine whether or not host notifications can be sent out when the host goes down, becomes
  unreachable, or recovers. If the host or service notification does not pass these options, <emphasis role="bold">the contact will not be
  notified</emphasis>. If it does pass these options, the notification gets passed to the next filter...</para>

  <note>
    <para>Notifications about host or service recoveries are only sent out if a notification was sent out for the original problem. It
    doesn't make sense to get a recovery notification for something you never knew was a problem...</para>
  </note>

  <para>The last filter that must be passed for each contact is the time period test. Each contact definition has a
  &lt;<emphasis>notification_period</emphasis>&gt; option that specifies which time period contains valid notification times for the
  contact. If the time that the notification is being made does not fall within a valid time range in the specified time period, <emphasis
  role="bold">the contact will not be notified</emphasis>. If it falls within a valid time range, the contact gets notified!</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Notification Methods</emphasis></para>

  <para>You can have &name-icinga; notify you of problems and recoveries pretty much anyway you want: pager, cellphone, email, instant
  message, audio alert, electric shocker, etc. How notifications are sent depend on the <link
  linkend="objectdefinitions-command">notification commands</link> that are defined in your <link linkend="config">object definition
  files</link>.</para>

  <note>
    <para>If you install &name-icinga; according to the <link linkend="quickstart">quickstart guide</link>, it should be configured to send
    email notifications. You can see the email notification commands that are used by viewing the contents of the following file:
    <emphasis>&url-icinga-base;/etc/objects/commands.cfg</emphasis>.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Specific notification methods (paging, etc.) are not directly incorporated into the &name-icinga; code as it just doesn't make much
  sense. The "core" of &name-icinga; is not designed to be an all-in-one application. If service checks were embedded in &name-icinga;' core
  it would be very difficult for users to add new check methods, modify existing checks, etc. Notifications work in a similiar manner. There
  are a thousand different ways to do notifications and there are already a lot of packages out there that handle the dirty work, so why
  re-invent the wheel and limit yourself to a bike tire? Its much easier to let an external entity (i.e. a simple script or a full-blown
  messaging system) do the messy stuff. Some messaging packages that can handle notifications for pagers and cellphones are listed below in
  the resource section.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Notification Type Macro</emphasis></para>

  <para>When crafting your notification commands, you need to take into account what type of notification is occurring. The <link
  linkend="macrolist-notificationtype">$NOTIFICATIONTYPE$</link> macro contains a string that identifies exactly that. The table below lists
  the possible values for the macro and their respective descriptions:</para>

  <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="10*" />

      <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="50*" />

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Value</emphasis> </para></entry>

          <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis> </para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>PROBLEM</para></entry>

          <entry><para>A service or host has just entered (or is still in) a problem state. If this is a service notification, it means the
          service is either in a WARNING, UNKNOWN or CRITICAL state. If this is a host notification, it means the host is in a DOWN or
          UNREACHABLE state.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>RECOVERY</para></entry>

          <entry><para>A service or host recovery has occurred. If this is a service notification, it means the service has just returned to
          an OK state. If it is a host notification, it means the host has just returned to an UP state.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</para></entry>

          <entry><para>This notification is an acknowledgement notification for a host or service problem. Acknowledgement notifications are
          initiated via the web interface by contacts for the particular host or service.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>FLAPPINGSTART</para></entry>

          <entry><para>The host or service has just started <link linkend="flapping">flapping</link>.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>FLAPPINGSTOP</para></entry>

          <entry><para>The host or service has just stopped <link linkend="flapping">flapping</link>.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>FLAPPINGDISABLED</para></entry>

          <entry><para>The host or service has just stopped <link linkend="flapping">flapping</link> because flap detection was
          disabled..</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>DOWNTIMESTART</para></entry>

          <entry><para>The host or service has just entered a period of <link linkend="downtime">scheduled downtime</link>. Future
          notifications will be supressed.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>DOWNTIMESTOP</para></entry>

          <entry><para>The host or service has just exited from a period of <link linkend="downtime">scheduled downtime</link>.
          Notifications about problems can now resume.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>DOWNTIMECANCELLED</para></entry>

          <entry><para>The period of <link linkend="downtime">scheduled downtime</link> for the host or service was just cancelled.
          Notifications about problems can now resume.</para></entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Helpful Resources</emphasis></para>

  <para>There are many ways you could configure &name-icinga; to send notifications out. Its up to you to decide which method(s) you want to
  use. Once you do that you'll have to install any necessary software and configure notification commands in your config files before you
  can use them. Here are just a few possible notification methods:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Email</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Pager</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Phone (SMS)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>WinPopup message</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Yahoo, ICQ, or MSN instant message</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Audio alerts</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>etc...</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Basically anything you can do from a command line can be tailored for use as a notification command.</para>

  <para>If you're looking for an alternative to using email for sending messages to your pager or cellphone, check out these packages. They
  could be used in conjuction with &name-icinga; to send out a notification via a modem when a problem arises. That way you don't have to
  rely on email to send notifications out (remember, email may *not* work if there are network problems). I haven't actually tried these
  packages myself, but others have reported success using them...</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><link xlink:href="http://www.gnokii.org/">Gnokii</link> (SMS software for contacting Nokia phones via GSM network)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link xlink:href="http://www.qpage.org/">QuickPage</link> (alphanumeric pager software)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link xlink:href="http://www.sendpage.org/">Sendpage</link> (paging software)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><link xlink:href="http://www.smsclient.org/">SMS Client</link> (command line utility for sending messages to pagers and mobile
      phones)</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>If you want to try out a non-traditional method of notification, you might want to mess around with audio alerts. If you want to
  have audio alerts played on the monitoring server (with synthesized speech), check out <link
  xlink:href="http://www.cstr.ed.ac.uk/projects/festival/">Festival</link>. If you'd rather leave the monitoring box alone and have audio
  alerts played on another box, check out the <link xlink:href="http://radscan.com/nas">Network Audio System (NAS)</link> and <link
  xlink:href="http://rplay.doit.org/">rplay</link> projects.</para>

  <indexterm zone="explanation_notifications">
    <primary>Notifications</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm zone="explanation_notifications">
    <primary>Notifications</primary>

    <secondary>Filter</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm zone="explanation_notifications">
    <primary>Notifications</primary>

    <secondary>Audio Alerts</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm zone="explanation_notifications">
    <primary>Gnokii</primary>
  </indexterm>
</section>
