<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="objectinheritance" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title><anchor xml:id="object_inheritance" />Object Inheritance</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

    <para>This documentation attempts to explain object inheritance and how it can be used in your <link linkend="objectdefinitions">object
    definitions</link>.</para>

    <para>If you are confused about how recursion and inheritance work after reading this, take a look at the sample object config files provided in
    the &name-icinga; distribution. If that still doesn't help, drop an email message with a <emphasis>detailed</emphasis> description of your problem
    to the <emphasis>icinga-users</emphasis> mailing list.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Basics</emphasis></para>

    <para>There are three variables affecting recursion and inheritance that are present in all object definitions. They are
    <emphasis>"indicated"</emphasis> as follows...</para>

    <screen> define <emphasis> someobjecttype</emphasis>{
       <emphasis> object-specific variables</emphasis> ...
        name           <emphasis> template_name</emphasis>
        use            <emphasis> name_of_template_to_use</emphasis>
        register        [0/1]
        }</screen>

    <para>The first variable is <emphasis>name</emphasis>. Its just a "template" name that can be referenced in other object definitions so they can
    inherit the objects properties/variables. Template names must be unique amongst objects of the same type, so you can't have two or more host
    definitions that have "hosttemplate" as their template name.</para>

    <para>The second variable is <emphasis>use</emphasis>. This is where you specify the name of the template object that you want to inherit
    properties/variables from. The name you specify for this variable must be defined as another object's template named (using the
    <emphasis>name</emphasis> variable).</para>

    <para>The third variable is <emphasis>register</emphasis>. This variable is used to indicate whether or not the object definition should be
    "registered" with &name-icinga;. By default, all object definitions are registered. If you are using a partial object definition as a template,
    you would want to prevent it from being registered (an example of this is provided later). Values are as follows: 0 = do NOT register object
    definition, 1 = register object definition (this is the default). This variable is NOT inherited; every (partial) object definition used as a
    template must explicitly set the <emphasis>register</emphasis> directive to be <emphasis>0</emphasis>. This prevents the need to override an
    inherited <emphasis>register</emphasis> directive with a value of <emphasis>1</emphasis> for every object that should be registered.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Local Variables vs. Inherited Variables</emphasis></para>

    <para>One important thing to understand with inheritance is that "local" object variables always take precedence over variables defined in the
    template object. Take a look at the following example of two host definitions (not all required variables have been supplied):</para>

    <screen> define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      5
                
        name                    hosttemplate1
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost2
        max_check_attempts      3
                
        use                     hosttemplate1
        }</screen>

    <para>You'll note that the definition for host <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis> has been defined as having <emphasis>hosttemplate1</emphasis> as its
    template name. The definition for host <emphasis>bighost2</emphasis> is using the definition of <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis> as its template
    object. Once &name-icinga; processes this data, the resulting definition of host <emphasis>bighost2</emphasis> would be equivalent to this
    definition:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        host_name               bighost2
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      3
        }</screen>

    <para>You can see that the <emphasis>check_command</emphasis> and <emphasis>notification_options</emphasis> variables were inherited from the
    template object (where host <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis> was defined). However, the <emphasis>host_name</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>max_check_attempts</emphasis> variables were not inherited from the template object because they were defined locally. Remember, locally
    defined variables override variables that would normally be inherited from a template object. That should be a fairly easy concept to
    understand.</para>

    <tip>
        <para>If you would like local string variables to be appended to inherited string values, you can do so. Read more about how to accomplish
        this <link linkend="objectinheritance-add_string">below</link>.</para>
    </tip>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Inheritance Chaining</emphasis></para>

    <para>Objects can inherit properties/variables from multiple levels of template objects. Take the following example:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      5
                
        name                    hosttemplate1
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost2
        max_check_attempts      3
                
        use                     hosttemplate1
                
        name                    hosttemplate2
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost3
                
        use                     hosttemplate2
        }</screen>

    <para>You'll notice that the definition of host <emphasis>bighost3</emphasis> inherits variables from the definition of host
    <emphasis>bighost2</emphasis>, which in turn inherits variables from the definition of host <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis>. Once &name-icinga;
    processes this configuration data, the resulting host definitions are equivalent to the following:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      5
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost2
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      3
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost3
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      3
        }</screen>

    <para>There is no inherent limit on how "deep" inheritance can go, but you'll probably want to limit yourself to at most a few levels in order to
    maintain sanity.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Using Incomplete Object Definitions as Templates</emphasis></para>

    <para>It is possible to use imcomplete object definitions as templates for use by other object definitions. By "incomplete" definition, I mean
    that all required variables in the object have not been supplied in the object definition. It may sound odd to use incomplete definitions as
    templates, but it is in fact recommended that you use them. Why? Well, they can serve as a set of defaults for use in all other object
    definitions. Take the following example:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      5
                
        name                    generichosttemplate
                
        register                0
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        address                 192.168.1.3
                
        use                     generichosthosttemplate
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost2
        address                 192.168.1.4
                
        use                     generichosthosttemplate
        }</screen>

    <para>Notice that the first host definition is incomplete because it is missing the required <emphasis>host_name</emphasis> variable. We don't
    need to supply a host name because we just want to use this definition as a generic host template. In order to prevent this definition from being
    registered with &name-icinga; as a normal host, we set the <emphasis>register</emphasis> variable to 0.</para>

    <para>The definitions of hosts <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis> and <emphasis>bighost2</emphasis> inherit their values from the generic host
    definition. The only variable we've chosed to override is the <emphasis>address</emphasis> variable. This means that both hosts will have the
    exact same properties, except for their <emphasis>host_name</emphasis> and <emphasis>address</emphasis> variables. Once &name-icinga; processes
    the config data in the example, the resulting host definitions would be equivalent to specifying the following:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        address                 192.168.1.3
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      5
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost2
        address                 192.168.1.4
        check_command           check-host-alive
        notification_options    d,u,r
        max_check_attempts      5
        }</screen>

    <para>At the very least, using a template definition for default variables will save you a lot of typing. It'll also save you a lot of headaches
    later if you want to change the default values of variables for a large number of hosts.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Custom Object Variables</emphasis></para>

    <para>Any <link linkend="customobjectvars">custom object variables</link> that you define in your host, service, or contact definition templates
    will be inherited just like other standard variables. Take the following example:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        _customvar1             somevalue  ; &lt;-- Custom host variable
        _snmp_community         public  ; &lt;-- Custom host variable
                
        name                    generichosttemplate
                
        register                0
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        address                 192.168.1.3
                
        use                     generichosthosttemplate
        }</screen>

    <para>The host <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis> will inherit the custom host variables <emphasis>_customvar1</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>_snmp_community</emphasis>, as well as their respective values, from the <emphasis>generichosttemplate</emphasis> definition. The
    effective result is a definition for <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis> that looks like this:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        address                 192.168.1.3
        _customvar1             somevalue
        _snmp_community         public
        }</screen>

    <para><anchor xml:id="objectinheritance-cancel_string" /><emphasis role="bold">Cancelling Inheritance of String Values</emphasis></para>

    <para>In some cases you may not want your host, service, or contact definitions to inherit values of string variables from the templates they
    reference. If this is the case, you can specify "<emphasis role="bold">null</emphasis>" (without quotes) as the value of the variable that you do
    not want to inherit. Take the following example:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        event_handler           my-event-handler-command
                
        name                    generichosttemplate
                
        register                0
        }

 define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        address                 192.168.1.3
        event_handler           null
                
        use                     generichosthosttemplate
        }</screen>

    <para>In this case, the host <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis> will not inherit the value of the <emphasis>event_handler</emphasis> variable that is
    defined in the <emphasis>generichosttemplate</emphasis>. The resulting effective definition of <emphasis>bighost1</emphasis> is the
    following:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        host_name               bighost1
        address                 192.168.1.3
        }</screen>

    <para><anchor xml:id="objectinheritance-add_string" /><emphasis role="bold">Additive Inheritance of String Values</emphasis></para>

    <para>&name-icinga; gives preference to local variables instead of values inherited from templates. In most cases local variable values override
    those that are defined in templates. In some cases it makes sense to allow &name-icinga; to use the values of inherited <emphasis>and</emphasis>
    local variables together.</para>

    <para>This "additive inheritance" can be accomplished by prepending the local variable value with a plus sign (<emphasis
    role="bold">+</emphasis>). This features is only available for standard (non-custom) variables that contain string values. Take the following
    example:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        hostgroups              all-servers
                
        name                    generichosttemplate
                
        register                0
        }

 define host{
        host_name               linuxserver1
        hostgroups              +linux-servers,web-servers
                
        use                     generichosthosttemplate
        }</screen>

    <para>In this case, the host <emphasis>linuxserver1</emphasis> will append the value of its local <emphasis>hostgroups</emphasis> variable to that
    from <emphasis>generichosttemplate</emphasis>. The resulting effective definition of <emphasis>linuxserver1</emphasis> is the following:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        host_name               linuxserver1
        hostgroups              all-servers,linux-servers,web-servers
        }</screen>

    <para><anchor xml:id="objectinheritance-implied_inheritance" /><emphasis role="bold">Implied Inheritance</emphasis></para>

    <para>Normally you have to either explicitly specify the value of a required variable in an object definition or inherit it from a template. There
    are a few exceptions to this rule, where &name-icinga; will assume that you want to use a value that instead comes from a related object. For
    example, the values of some service variables will be copied from the host the service is associated with if you don't otherwise specify
    them.</para>

    <para>The following table lists the object variables that will be implicitly inherited from related objects if you don't explicitly specify their
    value in your object definition or inherit them from a template.</para>

    <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="5*" />

            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="10*" />

            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="10*" />

            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Object Type</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Object Variable</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Implied Source</emphasis> </para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry align="left" morerows="2" valign="middle"><para> <emphasis role="bold">Services</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para> <emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> in the associated host definition</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis>notification_interval</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>notification_interval</emphasis> in the associated host definition</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis>notification_period</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>notification_period</emphasis> in the associated host definition</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry align="left" morerows="2" valign="middle"><para> <emphasis role="bold">Host Escalations</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para> <emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> in the associated host definition</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis>notification_interval</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>notification_interval</emphasis> in the associated host definition</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis>escalation_period</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>notification_period</emphasis> in the associated host definition</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry align="left" morerows="2" valign="middle"><para> <emphasis role="bold">Service Escalations</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para> <emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> in the associated service definition</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis>notification_interval</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>notification_interval</emphasis> in the associated service definition</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis>escalation_period</emphasis> </para></entry>

                    <entry><para><emphasis>notification_period</emphasis> in the associated service definition</para></entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para><anchor xml:id="objectinheritance-impliedescalations" /><emphasis role="bold">Implied/Additive Inheritance in Escalations</emphasis></para>

    <para>Service and host escalation definitions can make use of a special rule that combines the features of implied and additive inheritance. If
    escalations 1) do not inherit the values of their <emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> or <emphasis>contacts</emphasis> directives from another
    escalation template and 2) their <emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> or <emphasis>contacts</emphasis> directives begin with a plus sign (+), then
    the values of their corresponding host or service definition's <emphasis>contact_groups</emphasis> or <emphasis>contacts</emphasis> directives
    will be used in the additive inheritance logic.</para>

    <para>Confused? Here's an example:</para>

    <screen> define host{
        name            linux-server
        contact_groups  linux-admins
        ...
        }

 define hostescalation{
        host_name       linux-server
        contact_groups  +management
        ...
        }</screen>

    <para>This is a much simpler equivalent to:</para>

    <screen> define hostescalation{
        host_name       linux-server
        contact_groups  linux-admins,management
        ...
        }</screen>

    <para><anchor xml:id="objectinheritance-important_values" /><emphasis role="bold">Important values</emphasis></para>

    <para>Service templates can make use of a special rule which gives precedence to their check_command value. If the check_command is prefixed with
    an exclamation mark (!), then the template's check_command is marked as important and will be used over the check_command defined for the service
    (this is styled after CSS syntax, which uses ! as an important attribute).</para>

    <para>Why is this useful? It is mainly useful when setting a different check_command for distributed systems. You may want to set a freshness
    threshold and a check_command that forces the service into a failed state, but this doesn't work with the normal templating system. Using this
    important flag allows the custom check_command to be written, but a general distributed template can be used to overrule the check_command when
    used on a central Icinga-erver.</para>

    <para>For instance:</para>

    <screen># On master
define service {
        name                   service-distributed
        register               0
        active_checks_enabled  0
        check_freshness        1
        check_command          !set_to_stale
        }
# On slave
define service {
        name                   service-distributed
        register               0
        active_checks_enabled  1
        }
# Service definition, used by master and slave
define service {
        host_name              host1
        service_description    serviceA
        check_command          check_http...
        use                    service-distributed
        ...
        }</screen>

    <para><anchor xml:id="objectinheritance-multiple_templates" /><emphasis role="bold">Multiple Inheritance Sources</emphasis></para>

    <para>Thus far, all examples of inheritance have shown object definitions inheriting variables/values from just a single source. You are also able
    to inherit variables/values from multiple sources for more complex configurations, as shown below.</para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="50*" />

            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="50*" />

            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry><para> <screen># Generic host template
define host{
        name                    generic-host
        active_checks_enabled   1
        check_interval          10
        ...
        register                0
        }

# Development web server template
define host{
        name                    development-server
        check_interval          15
        notification_options    d,u,r
        ...
        register                0
        }

# Development web server
define host{
        use                     generic-host,development-server
        host_name               devweb1
        ...
        }</screen> </para></entry>

                    <entry align="center" valign="top"><para> <inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="../images/multiple-templates1.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject> </para></entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>In the example above, <emphasis>devweb1</emphasis> is inheriting variables/values from two sources: <emphasis>generic-host</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>development-server</emphasis>. You'll notice that a <emphasis>check_interval</emphasis> variable is defined in both sources. Since
    <emphasis>generic-host</emphasis> was the first template specified in <emphasis>devweb1</emphasis>'s <emphasis>use</emphasis> directive, its value
    for the <emphasis>check_interval</emphasis> variable is inherited by the <emphasis>devweb1</emphasis> host. After inheritance, the effective
    definition of <emphasis>devweb1</emphasis> would be as follows:</para>

    <screen># Development web server
define host{
        host_name               devweb1
        active_checks_enabled   1
        check_interval          10
        notification_options    d,u,r
        ...
        }</screen>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Precedence With Multiple Inheritance Sources</emphasis></para>

    <para>When you use multiple inheritance sources, it is important to know how &name-icinga; handles variables that are defined in multiple sources.
    In these cases &name-icinga; will use the variable/value from the first source that is specified in the <emphasis>use</emphasis> directive. Since
    inheritance sources can themselves inherit variables/values from one or more other sources, it can get tricky to figure out what variable/value
    pairs take precedence.</para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="50*" />

            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="50*" />

            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry align="left" valign="top"><para> Consider the following host definition that references three templates:</para> <screen> # Development web server
 define host{ 
       use        1,  4,  8 
       host_name  devweb1 ...
 } </screen> <para>If some of those referenced templates themselves inherit variables/values from one or more other templates, the precendence rules
                    are shown to the right.</para> <para>Testing, trial, and error will help you better understand exactly how things work in complex
                    inheritance situations like this. :-)</para></entry>

                    <entry align="center" valign="top"><para> <inlinemediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="../images/multiple-templates2.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
                            </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject> </para></entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <indexterm zone="object_inheritance">
        <primary>Object Inheritance</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm zone="objectinheritance-cancel_string">
        <primary>Object Inheritance</primary>

        <secondary>Cancelling Inheritance of String Values</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm zone="objectinheritance-add_string">
        <primary>Object Inheritance</primary>

        <secondary>Additive Inheritance of String Values</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm zone="objectinheritance-implied_inheritance">
        <primary>Object Inheritance</primary>

        <secondary>Implied Inheritance</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm zone="objectinheritance-impliedescalations">
        <primary>Object Inheritance</primary>

        <secondary>Implied/Additive Inheritance in Escalations</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm zone="objectinheritance-important_values">
        <primary>Object Inheritance</primary>

        <secondary>Important values</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm zone="objectinheritance-multiple_templates">
        <primary>Object Inheritance</primary>

        <secondary>Multiple Inheritance Sources</secondary>
    </indexterm>
</section>
