<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="plugins" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="Icinga_plugins" />&name-icinga; Plugins</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>Unlike many other monitoring tools, &name-icinga; does not include any internal mechanisms for checking the status of hosts and
  services on your network. Instead, &name-icinga; relies on external programs (called plugins) to do all the dirty work.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">What Are Plugins?</emphasis></para>

  <para>Plugins are compiled executables or scripts (Perl scripts, shell scripts, etc.) that can be run from a command line to check the
  status or a host or service. &name-icinga; uses the results from plugins to determine the current status of hosts and services on your
  network.</para>

  <para>&name-icinga; will execute a plugin whenever there is a need to check the status of a service or host. The plugin does
  <emphasis>something</emphasis> (notice the very general term) to perform the check and then simply returns the results to &name-icinga;.
  &name-icinga; will process the results that it receives from the plugin and take any necessary actions (running <link
  linkend="eventhandlers">event handlers</link>, sending out <link linkend="notifications">notifications</link>, etc).</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Plugins As An Abstraction Layer</emphasis></para>

  <para><inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/plugins.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject></para>

  <para>Plugins act as an abstraction layer between the monitoring logic present in the &name-icinga; daemon and the actual services and
  hosts that are being monitored.</para>

  <para>The upside of this type of plugin architecture is that you can monitor just about anything you can think of. If you can automate the
  process of checking something, you can monitor it with &name-icinga;. There are already a lot of plugins that have been created in order
  to monitor basic resources such as processor load, disk usage, ping rates, etc. If you want to monitor something else, take a look at the
  documentation on <link linkend="pluginapi">writing plugins</link> and roll your own. It's simple!</para>

  <para>The downside to this type of plugin architecture is the fact that &name-icinga; has absolutely no idea what it is that you're
  monitoring. You could be monitoring network traffic statistics, data error rates, room temperature, CPU voltage, fan speed, processor
  load, disk space, or the ability of your super-fantastic toaster to properly brown your bread in the morning... &name-icinga; doesn't
  understand the specifics of what's being monitored - it just tracks changes in the <emphasis>state</emphasis> of those resources. Only the
  plugins themselves know exactly what they're monitoring and how to perform the actual checks.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">What Plugins Are Available?</emphasis></para>

  <para>There are plugins currently available to monitor many different kinds of devices and services, including:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>HTTP, POP3, IMAP, FTP, SSH, DHCP</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>CPU Load, Disk Usage, Memory Usage, Current Users</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Unix/Linux, Windows, and Netware Servers</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Routers and Switches</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>etc.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Obtaining Plugins</emphasis></para>

  <para>Plugins are not distributed with &name-icinga;, but you can download the official &name-nagios; plugins and many additional plugins
  created and maintained by &name-nagios; and &name-icinga; users from the following locations:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>&name-nagios; Plugins Project: <link
      xlink:href="http://nagiosplug.sourceforge.net/">http://nagiosplug.sourceforge.net/</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&name-nagios; Downloads Page: <link xlink:href="http://www.nagios.org/download/">http://www.nagios.org/download/</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>MonitoringExchange.org: <link xlink:href="http://www.monitoringexchange.org">&url-monitoringexchange;</link></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><anchor xml:id="plugins-howto" /><emphasis role="bold">How Do I Use Plugin X?</emphasis></para>

  <para>Nearly all plugins will display basic usage information when you execute them using '-h' or '--help' on the command line. For
  example, if you want to know how the check_http plugin works or what options it accepts, you should try executing the following
  command:</para>

  <screen> $&gt; ./check_http --help</screen>

  <anchor xml:id="plugins-hints" />

  <important>
    <para>Always execute the plugin using the &name-icinga; user (specified using the directive icinga_user in
    <filename>icinga.cfg</filename>) because some plugins will create temporary files. If you're testing plugins with another user then the
    &name-icinga; user may not have the permissions to overwrite existing files later on. Using another user you will not be able to find
    out if the &name-icinga; user is allowed to access several files (e.g. shared libraries) at all.</para>

    <para>When testing it don't call the plugin using relative paths (i.e <emphasis>./check_test_plugin</emphasis>). Always use absolute
    paths because that's the way &name-icinga; does it (i.e. <emphasis>&url-icinga-libexec;/check_test_plugin</emphasis>).</para>

    <para>Please note that the &name-icinga; <emphasis>user</emphasis> has a different environment than the &name-icinga;
    <emphasis>process</emphasis>. Using the first the logins script have been executed and there is a terminal connected to the user session
    so successfully running the plugin from the command line doesn't (necessarly) mean that it will run when executed by the process.
    Furthermore the process will not use a shell per default but execute calls to popen/execvp instead depending on the command (popen in
    case the command line contains meta characters meaningful to the shell like <literal>!$^&amp;*()~[]\|{};&lt;&gt;?'"</literal>, execvp if
    no meta characters are present).</para>
  </important>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Switch to the &name-icinga; user</emphasis></para>

  <para>Switch to the &name-icinga; user as defined in <filename>icinga.cfg</filename> unless already done and clear the environment</para>

  <screen> #&gt; su - icinga
 #&gt; env -i</screen>

  <para>If you are logged in now then skip to "Extending the environment"</para>

  <para>Due to security awareness of the packager / sys admin this might fail because the account is not allowed to login. Please ask your
  sys admin to change that temporarily or do one of the following</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>get the current shell from <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> and change it by issuing something similar to <screen> #&gt; OLD_SHELL=`grep icinga /etc/passwd | sed 's/.*://'`
 #&gt; usermod -s /bin/sh icinga</screen>execute the command(s) after switching to the &name-icinga; user and clearing the environment as
      described above</para>

      <para>don't forget to restore the shell setting after testing and leaving the session <screen> #&gt; usermod -s $OLD_SHELL icinga</screen></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>execute the command using "sudo -u icinga"</para>

      <screen> #&gt; sudo -u icinga /usr/local/icinga/libexec/sample-plugin.pl ...</screen>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Extending the environment</emphasis></para>

  <para>Several checks (like check_oracle_health) depend on various environment variables to be set. Don't put these in
  <filename>.bashrc</filename> or similar user dependent files but choose a central location. The default init script sources the file
  <filename>/etc/sysconfig/icinga</filename> so that would be an ideal place. Don't use the init script itself because your changes might be
  lost during updates.</para>

  <para>Example of <filename>/etc/sysconfig/icinga</filename></para>

  <para><screen> export ORACLE_HOME=/usr/lib/oracle/11.2/client64
 export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=$ORACLE_HOME/lib
 export PATH=$PATH:$ORACLE_HOME</screen>After you logged in these variables are not set but doing so is pretty easy</para>

  <para><screen> $&gt; . /etc/sysconfig/icinga</screen>Please verify the settings<screen> $&gt; echo $ORACLE_HOME
 $&gt; echo $LD_LIBRARY_PATH
 $&gt; echo $PATH</screen></para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Integrating a new plugin</emphasis></para>

  <para>If you want to integrate a new plugin then please read the documentation (if any) before installing it. It may contain important
  information about the prerequisites like additional packages, (perl) modules and on how to install the plugin together with hints for your
  distribution.</para>

  <para>Sometimes you have to compile the plugin preparing the compile process using "./configure" with or without options. Please check the
  file config.log for errors regarding missing (devel) packages before issuing the actual compile command (mostly "make" or "make all"). In
  most cases the plugin is copied to the plugins directory (i.e. <emphasis>&url-icinga-libexec;</emphasis>) during "make install".</para>

  <para>Sometimes you have to alter the plugin to reflect your environment (i.e. path to "utils.pm", ...). You may create a logical link
  pointing to the plugin directory instead so you don't have to change the plugin to circumvent this issue easing plugin updates later
  on.</para>

  <para>After the installation of the plugin call it from the command line using the appropriate options. If this works then you can
  integrate it into &name-icinga;.</para>

  <para>Let's imagine you used the following call on the command line</para>

  <programlisting> $&gt; &url-icinga-libexec;/sample-plugin.pl -H 192.168.1.2 -a argument1 -p parameter -n 5</programlisting>

  <para>The command definition has to contain two directives</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>command_name: this is a short name identifying the command, let's use <emphasis>check_sample</emphasis></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>command_line: here you define the command to execute. You can specify the command you executed on the command line but that
      would be very inflexible. Normally the plugin directory (&url-icinga-libexec;) remains the same so we can use a <link
      linkend="macrolist-user">$USERn$</link> variable which is defined in resource.cfg. The IP-address changes from host to host. There is
      a macro called <link linkend="macrolist-hostaddress">$HOSTADDRESS$</link> which we can use for that purpose. The value of the
      arguments may vary so these should be flexible, too. This may lead to the following definition:</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <programlisting> define command{ 
    command_name check_sample
    command_line $USER1$/sample-plugin.pl -H $HOSTADDRESS$ -a $ARG1$ -p $ARG2$ -n $ARG3$
    }</programlisting>

  <para>Then we have to define the check_command directive which is part of the host/service definition starting with the short name
  followed by the arguments separated by exclamation marks (!):</para>

  <programlisting> check_command check_sample!argument1!parameter!5</programlisting>

  <para>As you can see the IP-address is not specified because it is taken from the host definition.</para>

  <anchor xml:id="plugins-hints2" />

  <para>In addition to the <link linkend="macros">macros</link> already mentioned there are a lot of others making life easier. Please
  note:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>All &name-icinga; macros use all upper case and are enclosed in dollar signs ($)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Most macros are only valid for some types of commands. If you try to use a macro for a type of command for which it is not valid
      you'll get a dollar sign ($) instead of the expected value</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="macrolist-user">$USERn$</link> macros can be used to "hide" sensitive information like passwords because
      these values are not shown in the web interface. Additionally they can be used to specify special characters which otherwise may lead
      to problems. One example would be <literal>USER99=;</literal>. This way you can use a semicolon which otherwise would be treated as
      start of a comment within your definitions</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Native non-english speaking persons should note that <link linkend="macrolist-hostaddress">$HOSTADDRESS$</link> is written with
      a double "D"</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Raw command line</emphasis></para>

  <para>Starting with &name-icinga; 1.6 the classic UI allows to inspect the raw command line including values from
  <filename>resource.cfg</filename>. Clicking on "ACTIVE" next to "Check type" within host/service check details will give access to this
  information. If you don't have defined a check yet choose "View Config" from the main menu on the left, then "Command expansion". Please
  note that the user has to be permitted explicitly using the directive <link
  linkend="configcgi-authorized_for_full_command_resolution">authorized_for_full_command_resolution</link> in
  <filename>cgi.cfg</filename> to see the values of variables from <filename>resource.cfg</filename>. The user running the web server must
  have read access on this file, too.</para>

  <para>If you intend to log the raw command line then change some directives in <filename>icinga.cfg</filename> to the following
  values</para>

  <screen> #  16 = Host/service checks
 # 256 = Commands
 debug_level=272
 debug_verbosity=2
 max_debug_file_size=1000000000</screen>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Threshold and ranges</emphasis></para>

  <para>Some plugins support specifying ranges for the warning and critical values. Please check the documentation if this is the case for
  the plugin you want to use. The following is an excerpt from the <link
  xlink:href="http://nagiosplug.sourceforge.net/developer-guidelines.html#THRESHOLDFORMAT">developer guidelines</link>:</para>

  <para>A range is defined as a start and end point (inclusive) on a numeric scale (possibly negative or positive infinity).</para>

  <para>A threshold is a range with an alert level (either warning or critical).</para>

  <para>The theory is that the plugin will do some sort of check which returns back a numerical value, or metric, which is then compared to
  the warning and critical thresholds.</para>

  <para>This is the generalised format for ranges:</para>

  <para><code>[@]start:end</code></para>

  <para>Notes:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>start = end if :end is not specified</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>start and ":" is not required if start=0</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>if range is of format "start:" and end is not specified, assume end is infinity</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>to specify negative infinity, use "~"</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>alert is raised if metric is outside start and end range (inclusive of endpoints)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>if range starts with "@", then alert if inside this range (inclusive of endpoints)</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <note>
    <para>Not all plugins are coded to expect ranges in this format yet.</para>
  </note>

  <para>Example ranges<informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Range definition</emphasis></entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Generate an alert if x...</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>10</entry>

            <entry>&lt; 0 or &gt; 10, (outside the range of {0 .. 10})</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>10:</entry>

            <entry>&lt; 10, (outside {10 .. infinity})</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>~:10</entry>

            <entry>&gt; 10, (outside the range of {-infinity .. 10})</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>10:20</entry>

            <entry>&lt; 10 or &gt; 20, (outside the range of {10 .. 20})</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>@10:20</entry>

            <entry>&lt;= 10 and &gt;= 20, (inside the range of {10 .. 20})</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <para>Command line examples<informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Command line</emphasis></entry>

            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>check_stuff -w10 -c20</entry>

            <entry>Critical if "stuff" is over 20, else warn if over 10 (will be critical if "stuff" is less than 0)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>check_stuff -w~:10 -c~:20</entry>

            <entry>Same as above. Negative "stuff" is OK</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>check_stuff -w10: -c20</entry>

            <entry>Critical if "stuff" is over 20, else warn if "stuff" is below 10 (will be critical if "stuff" is less than 0)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>check_stuff -c1:</entry>

            <entry>Critical if "stuff" is less than 1</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>check_stuff -w~:0 -c10</entry>

            <entry>Critical if "stuff" is above 10; Warn if "stuff" is above zero</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>check_stuff -c5:6</entry>

            <entry>The only noncritical range is 5:6</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>check_stuff -c@10:20</entry>

            <entry>Critical if "stuff" is 10 to 20 <emphasis role="bold">[1]</emphasis></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>check_stuff -w20:30 -c10:40</entry>

            <entry>Warning if "stuff" below 20 or above 30, critical if "stuff" is below 10 or above 40 <emphasis
            role="bold">[2]</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable></para>

  <note>
    <para>[1]: The command line of the developer guidelines seems to be lacking "@" otherwise the meaning would be wrong (and there wouldn't
    be an example for the @ notation)</para>

    <para>[2]: Please note that the last example shows nested ranges. This might not even work with every plugin supporting ranges. It was
    tested using check_snmp.</para>
  </note>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Activating the definition</emphasis></para>

  <para>Check the configuration using "/etc/init.d/icinga show-errors" and resolve any errors before issuing "/etc/init.d/icinga restart".
  Wait until the object is checked and look at the status details. There might be errors.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>"...resulted in a return code of 127" / "out of bounds"</para>

      <para>This means the plugin was not found at the specified location or that a file called from within the plugin was not found. If you
      use $USERn$ macros calling the plugin then make sure that the macro really points to the location where the plugin is (is the macro
      defined in resource.cfg?). Notification commands often call a mail program. Make sure that the path to the mail program is
      correct.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>"...resulted in a return code of 126"</para>

      <para>Mostly this indicates a permissions problem. The process might not be able to access / execute the plugin and/or other related
      files.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>"...resulted in a return code of 13".</para>

      <para>Mostly this indicates a permissions problem. The user might not be able to access / execute the plugin and/or other related
      files. This might happen if you tested a plugin as root which creates temporary files. The &name-icinga; user is not allowed to
      overwrite these files.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>"(null)"</para>

      <para>The internal call to execvp didn't return anything.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Plugin API</emphasis></para>

  <para>You can find information on the technical aspects of plugins, as well as how to go about creating your own custom plugins <link
  linkend="pluginapi">here</link>.</para>

  <indexterm zone="Icinga_plugins">
    <primary>Plugins</primary>

    <secondary>&name-icinga; Plugins</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm zone="plugins-howto">
    <primary>How Do I Use Plugin X?</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm zone="plugins-hints">
    <primary>Plugins</primary>

    <secondary>Integrating a new plugin</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm zone="plugins-hints">
    <primary>Plugins</primary>

    <secondary>Plugins and macros</secondary>
  </indexterm>
</section>
