<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="quickstart" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Quickstart Installation Guides</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold"><anchor xml:id="introduction_quickstart" />Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>These quickstart guides will provide you with simple instructions on how to install &name-icinga; from source and have it monitoring
  your local machine within 20 to 30 minutes. Advanced installation options and configuration are discussed elsewhere.</para>

  <para>Links to configuration tools and other addons can be found <link linkend="addons">here</link>.</para>

  <anchor xml:id="quickstart-packages" />
  <note><para>Instead of installing &name-icinga; from scratch you may want to use a package which might be available for your OS. Please
    take a look at the <link xlink:href="https://www.icinga.org/download/packages">table of packages</link>.
  </para></note>

  <para>Besides, a new quick install guide for using the &name-idoutils; of &name-icinga; is also available enabling you to use an RDBMS
  based on &name-mysql;, &name-oracle;, or &name-postgres;, respectively.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold"><anchor xml:id="guides_quickstart" />Guides</emphasis></para>

  <para>Quickstart installation guides are currently available for various Linux distributions (most common &name-fedora;, &name-ubuntu;,
  &name-opensuse;). Because some distributions are similar you may succeed to use these instructions for &name-redhat;, &name-centos;,
  &name-debian; and &name-sles; as well. Marcel Hecko provided a quickstart quide for &name-freebsd;.</para>

  <note>
    <para>Please note that sometimes names of packages change between different versions of the same OS so if you don't find the packages
    mentioned it might be a good idea to use your favourite search engine to find out the correct name.</para>
  </note>

  <para>The <link linkend="quickstart-icinga">Quickstart guide for &name-linux;</link> and <link
  linkend="quickstart-icinga-freebsd">Quickstart guide for &name-freebsd;</link>, resp., provide you with instructions on how to install
  &name-icinga;, basic plugins to check several things and the classical GUI accessible through your web browser. The look and feel is quite
  similar to &name-nagios; although the GUI offers some enhancements (extended CSV export, submit commands for a group of objects, etc.).
  There is no database involved and all information is stored in flat files. &name-web; is <emphasis>not</emphasis> available in this
  setup.</para>

  <para>Using the <link linkend="quickstart-idoutils">Quickstart guide including &name-idoutils;</link> and <link
  linkend="quickstart-idoutils-freebsd">Quickstart guide including &name-idoutils; on &name-freebsd;</link>, resp., you will get the things
  mentioned above plus a database (using &name-mysql;, &name-oracle;, or &name-postgres;) to store current and historical information. The
  database is <emphasis>not</emphasis> used to enable configuration via a web interface. There are several <link
  linkend="addons">addons</link> specialised on this and there are no plans for a builtin tool. The new web interface can be installed when
  you use this setup. There are <link linkend="icinga-web-scratch">separate instructions</link> on how
  to do this after you installed &name-icinga; and &name-idoutils;.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>See: <link linkend="quickstart-icinga">Quickstart guide for &name-linux;</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>See: <link linkend="quickstart-icinga-freebsd">Quickstart guide for &name-freebsd;</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>See: <link linkend="quickstart-idoutils">Quickstart guide including &name-idoutils;</link></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>See: <link linkend="quickstart-idoutils-freebsd">Quickstart guide including &name-idoutils; on &name-freebsd;</link></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>If you are installing &name-icinga; on an operating system or Linux distribution that isn't listed above, read <link
  linkend="quickstart-icinga">Quickstart guide for &name-linux;</link> for an overview on what you'll need to do.</para>

  <para>Command names, paths, etc. vary widely across different Operating Systems/Distributions, so you'll likely need to tweak the
  installation docs a bit to work for your particular case.</para>

  <indexterm zone="introduction_quickstart">
    <primary>Quickstart</primary>

    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm zone="quickstart-packages">
    <primary>Icinga-Packages</primary>
  </indexterm>
</section>
