<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="stalking" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title><anchor xml:id="state_stalking" />State Stalking</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Introduction</emphasis></para>

  <para>State "stalking" is a feature which is probably not going to used by most users. When enabled, it allows you to log
  changes in the output service and host checks even if the state of the host or service does not change. When stalking is enabled
  for a particular host or service, &name-icinga; will watch that host or service very carefully and log any changes it sees in
  the output of check results. As you'll see, it can be very helpful to you in later analysis of the log files.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">How Does It Work?</emphasis></para>

  <para>Under normal circumstances, the result of a host or service check is only logged if the host or service has changed state
  since it was last checked. There are a few exceptions to this, but for the most part, that's the rule.</para>

  <para>If you enable stalking for one or more states of a particular host or service, &name-icinga; will log the results of the
  host or service check if the output from the check differs from the output from the previous check. Take the following example
  of eight consecutive checks of a service:</para>

  <informaltable frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="5">
      <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="15*" />

      <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="15*" />

      <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="50*" />

      <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="10*" />

      <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="10*" />

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Service Check #:</emphasis> </para></entry>

          <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Service State:</emphasis> </para></entry>

          <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Service Check Output:</emphasis> </para></entry>

          <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Logged Normally</emphasis> </para></entry>

          <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">Logged With Stalking</emphasis> </para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>x</para></entry>

          <entry><para>OK</para></entry>

          <entry><para>RAID array optimal</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>x+1</para></entry>

          <entry><para>OK</para></entry>

          <entry><para>RAID array optimal</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>x+2</para></entry>

          <entry><para>WARNING</para></entry>

          <entry><para>RAID array degraded (1 drive bad, 1 hot spare rebuilding)</para></entry>

          <entry><para> <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> </para></entry>

          <entry><para> <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> </para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>x+3</para></entry>

          <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

          <entry><para>RAID array degraded (2 drives bad, 1 host spare online, 1 hot spare rebuilding)</para></entry>

          <entry><para> <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> </para></entry>

          <entry><para> <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> </para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>x+4</para></entry>

          <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

          <entry><para>RAID array degraded (3 drives bad, 2 hot spares online)</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>

          <entry><para> <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> </para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>x+5</para></entry>

          <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

          <entry><para>RAID array failed</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>

          <entry><para> <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/checkmark.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> </para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>x+6</para></entry>

          <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

          <entry><para>RAID array failed</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para>x+7</para></entry>

          <entry><para>CRITICAL</para></entry>

          <entry><para>RAID array failed</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>

          <entry><para>-</para></entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para>Given this sequence of checks, you would normally only see two log entries for this catastrophe. The first one would occur
  at service check x+2 when the service changed from an OK state to a WARNING state. The second log entry would occur at service
  check x+3 when the service changed from a WARNING state to a CRITICAL state.</para>

  <para>For whatever reason, you may like to have the complete history of this catastrophe in your log files. Perhaps to help
  explain to your manager how quickly the situation got out of control, perhaps just to laugh at it over a couple of drinks at the
  local pub...</para>

  <para>Well, if you had enabled stalking of this service for CRITICAL states, you would have events at x+4 and x+5 logged in
  addition to the events at x+2 and x+3. Why is this? With state stalking enabled, &name-icinga; would have examined the output
  from each service check to see if it differed from the output of the previous check. If the output differed and the state of the
  service didn't change between the two checks, the result of the newer service check would get logged.</para>

  <para>A similiar example of stalking might be on a service that checks your web server. If the check_http plugin first returns a
  WARNING state because of a 404 error and on subsequent checks returns a WARNING state because of a particular pattern not being
  found, you might want to know that. If you didn't enable state stalking for WARNING states of the service, only the first
  WARNING state event (the 404 error) would be logged and you wouldn't have any idea (looking back in the archived logs) that
  future WARNING states were not due to a 404, but rather some text pattern that could not be found in the returned web
  page.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Should I Enable Stalking?</emphasis></para>

  <para>First, you must decide if you have a real need to analyze archived log data to find the exact cause of a problem. You may
  decide you need this feature for some hosts or services, but not for all. You may also find that you only have a need to enable
  stalking for some host or service states, rather than all of them. For example, you may decide to enable stalking for WARNING
  and CRITICAL states of a service, but not for OK and UNKNOWN states.</para>

  <para>The decision to to enable state stalking for a particular host or service will also depend on the plugin that you use to
  check that host or service. If the plugin always returns the same text output for a particular state, there is no reason to
  enable stalking for that state.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">How Do I Enable Stalking?</emphasis></para>

  <para>You can enable state stalking for hosts and services by using the <emphasis>stalking_options</emphasis> directive in <link
  linkend="configobject">host and service definitions</link>.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">How Does Stalking Differ From Volatile Services?</emphasis></para>

  <para><link linkend="volatileservices">Volatile services</link> are similar, but will cause notifications and event handlers to
  run. Stalking is purely for logging purposes.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Caveats</emphasis></para>

  <para>You should be aware that there are some potential pitfalls with enabling stalking. These all relate to the reporting
  functions found in various <link linkend="cgis">CGIs</link> (histogram, alert summary, etc.). Because state stalking will cause
  additional alert entries to be logged, the data produced by the reports will show evidence of inflated numbers of alerts.</para>

  <para>As a general rule, I would suggest that you <emphasis>not</emphasis> enable stalking for hosts and services without
  thinking things through. Still, it's there if you need and want it.</para>
  <indexterm zone="state_stalking"><primary>State Stalking</primary></indexterm>
</section>
